# PAOLO HILARIO RESUME

428 Merced Ct. | Corona, CA. 92880 | 909.525.6120 | cgsoldier@gmail.com | http://www.paolohilario.com

#### CAREER SUMMARY

A Product Development / Technical Director specializing in systems and process integration for Architecture, Engineering, and Construction. With a primary focus in the use of technology to solve problems relating to Processes, Business Systems, Information, Communication, and Collaboration within the AEC Industry. More than 8+ years of experience in building high functioning creative and technical teams as well as the strategic planning and tactical execution of enterprise/industry wide process and technology programs.

#### **OBJECTIVE**

A leadership position within a progressive AEC or Software Development firm focused on innovating processes and technology within the AEC Industry that would fully utilize my skills and experience building high functioning teams and the planning and execution of challenging programs.

#### PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

#### Project Management Skills

SDLC – Software Development Life Cycle Agile Software Development – XP/Scrum Six Sigma Green Belt

#### **Programming Languages**

Desktop: C# .NET, WPF, WinForms, WCF, OBJ-C, Java (J2EE)

Database: MS Access, MS SQL Server 2005 & 2008 R2, MSSQL Compact, MySql, SQLite

Script Languages: MaxScript, MelScript, AutoCAD Lisp

Mobile: IOS, Android

Web Development: HTML, CSS, JavaScript

## Developement Software

VersionOne, TeamCity, Subversion, Git, Microsoft TFS, MS Build, Visual Paradigm UML Eclipse, Visual Studio 2005-2010, Expression Blend, XCode, Dreamweaver

# AEC, BIM, VDC Software

Autodesk AutoCAD 14 – 2011, AutoCAD Architecture 2008-2011, Revit 2009 – 2011, NavisWorks 9 - 2011 Solibri Model Checker, Synchro Professional, Innovaya Visual QTO

### Media Production Software

Autodesk 3DSMAX 3.5 - 2011, Maya 2010 - 2011 Adobe Illustrator, Photoshop, Premiere, After Effects, InDesign, Flash; Release CS2 - CS5 Pixologic Zbrush 2 - 4, Eyeon Fusion 5 - 6.1, Nuke, Boujou, Apple Final Cut Studio

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Scenario Virtual Project Delivery, Anaheim CA. Director of Product Development

Conceptualized, architected, and managed the development of Scenario VPD's entire suite of products, a framework that enables companies within the AEC Industry to effectively manage information, processes, and organizations involved in delivering projects using BIM/VDC.

Architected and managed the development of the proprietary software technology and design processes used by KHS&S International's Rockwork and Water Technologies Division.

JAN 2008 - Present

Responsible for assembling and managing a high functioning software development team, responsible for resource planning, product development schedules, advanced research & development, programming, and managing Scenario VPD's overall product & technology roadmap.

## Technical Director / Design Manager

Developed an end to end design development process pipeline for the newly formed 3D Design Department focused on the concept development, design, fabrication, and construction of theme park attractions and rockwork features. Responsible for the research, development, and implementation of BIM & VDC based processes for design, engineering, and computer assisted fabrication departments. Developed all proprietary in-house tools and software to facilitate the integration and automation of the design and production pipeline.

Assembled and Managed the 3D Design Department, including resource planning, project scheduling, and served as the technical advisor to specific projects on an as-needed basis.

## Lucetius Design, Covina CA. Technical Director

Re-Engineered the existing 3D Modeling, Animation, and Video Compositing pipeline. Designed and Developed all in-house production tools resulting in a 40% reduction in Project Delivery Schedules.

## Headrick & Associates, San Clemente CA Technical Director / CG Supervisor

Developed an end to end 3D Modeling, Animation, and Video Compositing pipeline for a startup studio including all hardware and software infrastructure. Designed and Developed all in-house production tools.

# Focus 360, Laguna Nigel CA. Project Lead / Animation Lead

Project Lead, Animation Lead for Architectural Pre-Visualization of various development projects.

# Wirt Design Group, Pasadena CA 3D Pre-Visualization Specialist

Concept Development, Pre-Visualization, and 3D Constructability Review for Commercial Interiors

# Shercon Inc., Cypress CA Applications Engineer

Engineered custom masking products for the rubber products division, programmed CNC wire bending machines for a new paint hook line of products, and developed and maintained technical specification documents.

# APR 2006 - DEC 2007

JUN 2004 - APR 2006

JAN 2002 - JUN 2004

APR 2000 - JAN 2002

AUG 1998 - APR 2000

#### **EDUCATION**

University of California, Irvine, CA

Certificate in Project Management, PMP

Present

University of California, Irvine, CA

Certificate in Six Sigma Lean, SSGB

Present

Marshall University, Huntington, WV

B.A. in Fine Arts

Major: Graphic Design & New Media

Minor: Communications

1994 - 1998

#### ADVISORY BOARDS

Stanford University - Center for Integrated Facilities Engineering

Member - Technical Advisory Committee

**2010 - Present** 

#### PUBLICATIONS AND PAPERS

BIMFO Blog - BIM & VDC Technology and Processes http://bmfo.paolohilario.com

#### **PATENTS**

Dimensioned Modeling System

Inventors: Paolo Hilario et al.

U.S Patent Number 20100241477

A construction project management system comprising: at least one modeling workflow application configured to provide functionality for creating... http://www.fags.org/patents/app/20100241477

Integration System Supporting Dimensioned Modeling System

Inventors: Paolo Hilario et al.

A computer implemented system operative to store construction project information originating from multiple sources and to apply rules... http://www.faqs.org/patents/app/20100241471

U.S Patent Number 20100241471

Method of Three-Dimensional Theming

Inventors: Paolo Hilario et al.

A method of fabricating a thematic design article, comprising the steps of: formulating from a three-dimensional computer model of the article... http://www.faqs.org/patents/app/20090113969

U.S Patent Number 20090113969

### PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

- U.S. Green Building Council
- Project Management Institute
- Lean Construction Institute
- American Society for Quality
- International Society of Six Sigma Professionals

## PERSONAL INTERESTS

- · Fishing, Camping, Archery, Skeet & Trap Shooting
- Physics, Sociology, Psychology, Computing